[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
[Music]
welcome everyone to the stoa i am peter
limberg the steward of the stoa
and today we have a very special guest
peter and i'm going to like just
patiently say his last name peter
shostad
h is here today um to have a talk on
neo nihilism the philosophy of power
and peter uh he he's
better known today or he speaks more on
psychedelics and and uh pan psychism
um but i kind of reached out to him
wanting him
to talk about neo nihilism this
philosophy of power because that's how
he first came on my radar
years ago um i think was warren ellis
the comic book author
gave him a nice plug and i read it and i
was like huh this is a really
interesting
take and i always wanted to talk to him
i never got a chance to do it on the
former podcast
and so i thought this was a perfect
opportunity to do so here at the stoa
so how today is going to work i'm going
to actually the mc today is ariel
friedman and i'll hand it her over to
her she'll explain what the q a process
introduce peter and then she'll have a
discussion with him then pivot to the q
a
so ariel runs a podcast called the
multiversity project
where former anarchists and discuss
cultureware meaning crisis and stuff
like that
and she also does something called the
dangerous space here at stoa where we
safely talk about dangerous ideas and so
after the the recorded
uh part that hour whoever wants to stay
afterwards we'll have like a 30 minute
dangerous space session
uh and ariel has a little bit spotty
wi-fi connection so i might have to jump
in but uh
we'll give it a shot um so i'll take uh
ariel and
right now you can unmute yourself
cool thanks peter uh yeah so today we're
going to be talking about neonialism
with peter show said h
neonialism it's philosophy he developed
based on
hume schopenhauer and nietzsche's
philosophy and the way today is going to
go is we're going to have a brief
interview portion while i'll ask peter
some questions to kind of open up
open up the space around his ideas and
if you guys have questions like as they
come up you just put them in the chat
and then we're going to have a period
where we'll ask peter some of your
questions
so this is going to end up on youtube so
if you don't want uh
your face and person appearing on
youtube you can just uh
you know we'll ask if you will ask you
if you go if you want to read your own
question if you don't then then i can
just read your question for you or peter
can
so is that is that clear if you don't
want to appear on youtube we can read
your question and if you do
then you can read your own question you
get the chance to do that
after that peter's going to announce
some upcoming events and then post the
event we'll have a little
discussion around around some of these
some of the topics that came out today
uh so let's get right into it um peter
uh so one thing we're kind of wondering
about is
like before we really get into like the
nitty-gritty of your philosophy
i was feeling kind of curious like how
you how you got to know nihilism like
what was your journey to getting there
right well um i guess um nietzsche is
mostly responsible for that
so i um you know started studying nature
when i was 18 in my bachelor's degree
and it sort of um
along with some of the other great
philosophy sort of blows your mind
completely and just makes you question
all the axioms
and um so that's the beginning of it but
i'd
also reading hume of course uh either
philosophy bachelors i should say
and um and then in london i was working
at college where i was teaching and each
is beyond good and evil his
one of his last books for six years and
uh
on top of that i was teaching um
epistemologies
um and then a nice kind of um
a nice kind of um connection occurred
where a lot of the sort of
20th century epistemologies on ethics
that i was teaching sort of um
cohered with nietzsche's view views on
good good and evil
and um and i decided to
just write a quick essay in a very um
kind of um you know forceful manner so
it's a kind of style of writing which i
don't normally do it's not
i don't normally speak like that but i
thought i'd try a bit of hyperbole
but keep it as concise as possible just
to express
the fundamental aspects of
nature hume as you say actually from
schopenhauer because a lot of niches
works based on shopping hours
so i um yeah so i just wrote this quick
uh
essay it was ten what eleven thousand
words or so
put it online and um and then it became
a chapter in my book numerous a year
later or so
um and i didn't think much of it it was
just really to put
i didn't think it would be you know red
or anything but but um then out of the
blue yeah
um warren ellis
uh suddenly one day i actually had a
peek in sales i thought why the hell
what's happening here and i discovered
that this uh quite a well-known comic
books uh
writer or an ellis um he sort of based
this um
recreation of karnak this this um
comic character superhero partly on the
animalism
and then it became uh yeah more popular
after that but then i personally sort of
moved on from that as
peter limberg was saying i sort of uh
then got into um
more shopping hours pan psychism um and
then ultimately whitehead and
and then i took some magic mushrooms
which kind of changed my interests quite
considerably
and i got into psychedelic philosophy um
but that's
yeah that's basically the way it is
cool cool thank you so what is
neo-nihilism
what is neo-nihilism well okay so uh
um it's ultimately the doctrine
that um and this is really nothing
new this was i mean you find this in
plato with
characters like throughout the maccas
and galaxies but ultimately
the the argument that there are there
are no such things as objective
morals objective values um but it's not
a sort of traditional analysis which
says that there are no values there is
no meaning to life and there is no truth
that's why i added the prefix neo it's
um
compatible with the multiplicity of
values in the world
and one's own self evaluation but
ultimately the ultimate point of it is
before you get into
all the details that any moral
proposition or any normative moral
proposition in other words when you tell
someone
or people what they ought to do when you
issue a command or an imperative
um ultimately that cannot be based uh
that cannot be a truth statement it
can't be true
um it's ultimately a means of trying to
that's that's it in a nutshell
okay cool do you want to elaborate on
the power bit a bit
like how neo-nihilism connects to power
um well this is the nietzschean bit
really
so um there are in the 20th century
there were a number of philosophers who
said that um you know
that moral propositions like i ought not
to lie i know what not to steal one will
not steal
um these are either meaningless or they
are false
or non-cognitive or whatever there's
different versions of that
um but they were never based on those
were mostly based on a kind of um
an empiricism or a logical positivism
which could never like metaphysically
uh substantiate those claims so what
i've done
in neo nihilism is i've linked this kind
of epistemological view that
ethical propositions don't have truth
value ultimately
to a metaphysics of power based on
nietzsche's will to power willism act
which was um which for those who don't
know is
um a view that
um at the fundamental level of all
things
and there are different interpretations
of this nature but ultimately
as you find out especially in from 1886
onwards from beyond good and evil
onwards
um there's this notion that at the
fundamental level
of reality below matter even
there is everything strives for power
and that doesn't that doesn't mean greed
doesn't mean conscious greed or power as
we understand it
it's more akin to sort of growth but
it's not growth
as as we understand it either it's um
it's nietzsche calls it a pathos
a feeling there's a feeling a desire to
develop basically this is how i see the
world of power this is something
nietzsche sort of um spoke about more
and more as
as he got older and he was actually
going to name a book the will to power
then he changed it and then his sister
and other editors created this book of
late
notes and they called it the will to
power so this is not the book that he
was really planning
well this was not the book he was
planning to write because it's just
notebooks
but nonetheless he was planning to write
a book on the world to power
um but of course in 1889 he went
he suffered a mental breakdown he went
you know insane and colloquial
and uh never completed that but i think
he was on
he was on a mission to create this sort
of metaphysics of
of power which could substantiate
uh moral truth claims and and uh
you know and politics and and so on so
forth
so i suppose yeah the po ultimately when
you say i mean
coming back to neonatalism then when you
say something like um
you know one or not to lie or something
like that ultimately
what this is based on is power it's
ultimately a person or a group
trying to tell other people um how they
should behave
they're not stating a fact they're not
saying you know if i said like this
table is made of wood
that could be that could be verified and
or falsified and um
it would be a statement of fact but if i
said one or not to lie
proposition is very similar to that
statement but of course it's not
verifiable
um and it's very hard ultimately
to substantiate that and of course there
are very many normative ethics
utilitarianism deontology so on so forth
but ultimately when you get to the
fundamental question of you know
why do you believe this if you don't
believe in god
importantly um then it comes to nothing
so this is in a way a continuation
or a kind of expression of nietzsche's
claim that god is dead because what he
meant by that is
not simply the fact that we you know we
don't believe in him anymore
the chris judeo christian god but rather
the important part of that expression is
that
if you don't believe in this um
biblical god then you have if you don't
believe in the christian
god he says explicitly you have no right
to christian morals
and even nietzsche's point
really is criticism western culture is
that
even if you don't believe in
christianity explicitly most people
still assume
christian morals because they've had two
thousand years to sort of embed
themselves within the western mind
um but ultimately this is based on god
as both law giver
and as um a kind of a
creator that gives humanity a purpose
and gives each human a purpose
if you take away that creator and that
law giver
um you're sort of left in this abyss you
know the
sort of 20th century existentialists
consider this sort of negative in a way
or liberating depending on who you read
but ultimately um nietzsche's point is
if you don't believe in the christian
god you've got no right to christian
morals
and for him christian morals included
utilitarianism and socialism and so on
um and in fact any ism any ideology
capitalism or marxism whatever have you
you've got no right to that so where
does that leave you
well if you think that values are only
those christian values that legacy of
christian values that we have inherited
then of course it's very negative and
then you get into this kind of um
into this um melancholy abyss where you
think everything's pointless
but this is of course only based on a
belief that these are the only values
this is why nietzsche also speaks about
you know this distinction between master
and slave morality that
um you know christianity is the epitome
of slave morality
and this has been so influential that
we've assumed that to be morality itself
but of course nietzsche speaks about you
know former moralities other moralities
around the world
um so it's not as if destroying these
western values means there are no values
it rather emancipates person to say
number one
one can create the values one pleases
and secondly it's kind of emancipatory
because it
it one doesn't take any kind of moral
impositions as truthful you know someone
says you should do this
you wonder what to do that or society
should be like this or we must get rid
of this
or this is evil and so on you know it's
sort of uh
it makes you well immediately makes you
say why you know what what's the basis
of that
upon which standard you know of morality
and if it is based on a normative
morality which is
rare but then you ask well
can you ultimately find this objective
moral upon which
it is based um
yeah so um so that's more nature but
anyway
so it's implementing that it's also also
i should say
you know you read nietzsche nietzsche is
very critical of shopping now in the
later works but then when you reach open
now you realize how much shopping now it
actually influenced nietzsche
and um anyway like so shopping how are
bringing in alice and bringing shopping
as well because he said
you know he was an ethicist but he
wasn't a normative
ethicist and this is a very important
distinction in that i'm making
in um neo-nihilism and chauvinal said
that
um the morals that we have inherited
are um imperative morals you know can't
criticizes can't those sort of post
canteen he's
criticized can't for just simply
assuming that morals must be in the
imperative form
thou shalt you know um as opposed to the
descriptive form
which i'll explain in a minute and this
i mean
shopping now even uses the term slave
morals which people just
attribute to nietzsche but um it's in
shop an hour already
but nietzsche's criticism of
schopenhauer is that he still assumes
the kind of christian legacy
because because he thinks that well
these these christian values are the
greatest values and they're not true so
one should just simply
fall into pessimism but let me just um
explain this difference this fundamental
difference then between prescriptive and
descriptive ethics
so and this is the first part of the
essay really
neonatalism um there's two ways of
speaking about ethics generally or one
can speak about them in two general ways
um so descriptively like an
anthropologist would go to another
society or look in the past and say
these people believe this you know the
ancient spartans believed this
ancient athenians believed this and they
thought this was good and this was evil
and country-wise another
society thought complete opposite and um
you know in this society this small
section of the society we believe this
that's just describing people's moral
beliefs and behaviors and that's fine
that's anthropological sociological
but as opposed to that descriptive
morality
most people when they talk when you say
talk about ethics and morality
they consider it to be prescriptive so
that's when you prescribe
actions when you say things um are like
this but they ought to be like this
and what this these people did was wrong
and what these people did was right and
so on
and and that is what i take issue with
neonatalism that form of ethics
that um because ultimately yeah this is
really fundamentally
ultimately it assumes a kind of
platonism that there's
a transcendent form of the good
ultimately in most cases
um i remember when i was phd student
exeter
every two weeks or so we had an ethics
paper in little
group of phd students and professors and
ultimately all these all these ethical
papers came down to this fun
fundamental point you know but how do
you ultimately substantiate
that axiom that ethical axiom and um
that's what neolinism tries to break
down
of course it doesn't prescribe any
actions either no it doesn't say you
know this is not evil therefore
you should do this whatever because that
would also be prescriptive
it just leaves you it's just sort of um
it's like a
deletion mechanism it just sort of tr
seeks to at least
um obliterate this kind of belief that
is so prevalent still
so there you go that's sort of like it's
probably a bit messy in the wrong order
but those are the fundamental points nah
that's that's great that's great you
covered pretty much all the ground you
want to get to in the interview portion
so
that was a great intro yeah why don't we
move on to some people's
questions because i see the chats blown
up a bit
um yeah rain do you want to ask uh
one of your questions okay so just sorry
just to review what we're gonna do is
i'm gonna pick someone
you guys can either ask your question
yourself or if you don't wanna do that
just shake your head or
stay silent and then i can ask your
question for you if you don't want to
appear on youtube
i'm going to ask some of you guys have
multiple questions in there so i'm going
to ask by calling you just pick one
so rain go for it
sure thanks um hi peter hi
um so i was wondering how how
neo-nihilism accounts for
uh different studies that have shown
moral stages of development
um you know kohlberg's comes to mind but
there are other
models that show a similar progression
from
pre-conventional to conventional to
post-conventional and
you know it's scientifically validated
and it seems to be true across
different uh cultures um
yeah how does neo-nihilism account for
that developmental aspect of morality
was it kolberg who committed suicide but
jumping off a cliff
i think it was yeah um okay yeah now
i've read kohlberg many years ago
um and this theory of development i mean
i would say this
how i get and this will always be my
answer to probably everything
like how when you talk about moral
progression
how do you know what the standard is to
which
one is progressing how is that
determined
um so with kohlberg it seems to he just
assumes
i can't remember the details of him now
but it's um
one is just like you don't want to be
told off at the primal level right and
then
later on it's um one has some kind of
conscience
whereby one doesn't care what what other
people think something like this right
but ultimately the point is this um this
kind of theory assumes a morality
assumes a standard like this is the
greatest form of
uh morals there are and then applies
that standard
to different societies and says look
this society's here we're in the middle
somewhere
you know ideally would be at the top but
my question would be how do you
how do you substantiate that standard in
the first place
how did kohlberg know what was moral in
order for him to talk about progression
i mean this is this is the fundamental
question well i i can answer that a
little bit
yeah so the progressive aspect is not
based
on um a projected ontology
of an ultimate morality but it's an
observation that
um people go from premoral to moral
but if you observe and study
descriptively they never go backwards
from moral to premoral or from or sorry
from conventional to pre-conventional so
there is a observable linearity
that's what makes it developmental
okay but that still i would say that
that
notion of um development is based
on a preconceived standard um and also
is it true that we don't go back i mean
if you think about you know
like in england here i mean you think
about the romans and civilized romans
you know they invaded
50 bc and then they stayed until about
480. um
after that you know the saxons came they
were brutal you know we
really returned to a sort of what was
generally considered a primitive form of
morality
and it took um you know thousand years
again to sort of
reattain that roman level of um
etiquette
and civil civility if you call the
romans civilized of course i mean like
you know they were
they were also you know extreme
colonizers and imperialists of course
you know
so but my ultimate point is that um okay
yeah you you can see developments and
generally um
morals change but to say they progress i
mean i'm
in a descriptive sense yeah you can see
different societies and you can see how
they change
and that's descriptive morality as i was
saying and that's absolutely that's a
legitimate
science you know social sociology or
anthropology or whatever but or history
but um
to say that one society is somehow
superior to another society
is a proposition that can't be
in any way um validated
so like one you know
for example if the i don't know if
if like if you take um the viking
society
who um who valued like a hard heart
and they this valued compassion in many
cases
um if they were to see the society of
sweden today um my homeland
they would think oh my god what's
happened to these people you know
they've become
they've really retrogressed you know
they've really become
sops and so on now of course today would
say yeah but you these were brutal
barbarians who didn't know what was
right or wrong
but but i would say no we can't judge it
that way
we can just say they had a different
form of morality
you can't you simply can't talk about
progress or retrogress
maybe let's maybe let's move on to
another another question this is
we wanna there's a bunch of in the chat
but this is a really interesting
exchange so i appreciate it
we had some back and forth there um
rachel uh do you want to ask your
question about trolls
yes hi so yeah thank you
funny and good good to finally put a
face to the name and the thinking
i wanted to ask you as uh yeah
anichi and a fellow nietzschean right um
the philosophy of power and the
nihilistic trolls
who are beyond good and evil in a really
degenerate
annoying way you know like the the
people who
the the 4chan crowd you know
they're hyper nihilistic how do you
suggest
that um have you dealt with these people
first i i haven't actually no it's uh
for us to hear about them
um just commenters commenters on youtube
videos with low
iqs have you dealt with people like that
yeah yeah okay yeah
i mean i ignore i mean i agree with
people like this immediately you know
that's why i don't know about them i
i wish i was you on stupid but my
question um
about all of this is when these people
who refer to themselves as
nihilists begin you know talking about
nietzsche
and you know just being being
nihilist in this degrading way
how do you suggest um i guess ignoring
them would be the answer for awesome but
did you have um
another solution maybe like a through
the ages
kind of conclusion i'm just how do you
feel about all of this as a whole
um i need you said something like the
the answer to a low browse a clenched
fist
of course you can't reply that on the
line can you so that's not the question
um i don't know i mean i just i just um
yeah trolls on the internet i mean i
just uh
just ignore them now i've i realized
that number one there's just no point
debating anything with them because
they'll never concede and
so it's just frustrating you just can't
win so i just
just completely ignore them and and try
to not let it
affect me in any emotional manner i must
admit i haven't received
that i have when i was younger i did
yeah but um
another thing about a lot of followers
of nietzsche and i admit this and i hope
i'm not one myself but they're really
annoying
you know this kind of nietzsche fanboy
club
um and nietzsche does appeal to like men
in their 20s
quite often i notice that's you know i
and i'm guilty of that appeal to me then
um and that's sort of why i moved on to
schopenhauer and then whitehead and
bergson people like that afterwards
um and i don't think nietzsche was right
about everything at all i mean he also
he
you know personally he was in many ways
failure but um if you are not in a moral
sense
but um yeah how'd you deal with them i
mean i think you've suffered from them
then obviously haven't you recently
um i don't yeah
i don't i don't know i just um i just
wish they weren't like degrading
nietzsche's name
because nietzsche was so pivotal to me
growing up
yeah it's just insulting to
his work yeah there's i mean he would be
ashamed and actually he um
he was i remember nietzsche wrote about
the anti-semites you know he said he
called them you know
barking dogs because he said he found
out his name was link some anti-semites
were talking about
uh him as as one of their own and he was
aghast by this
and of course he was very ashamed of his
sister elizabeth for marrying a sort of
leading ant you know
anti-semite aryan who created this
colony in south america you know it's
blonde children
and the legacy still remains strangely
um but he was very ashamed of this
and i think likewise you'd be ashamed of
most of his followers today perhaps even
me i don't know but
um but um yeah you know uh
you have to have a you know you have i
think anyone can read beyond good and
evil and say they're a nietzschean right
and it's
you know they they need to prove their i
think they need to prove themselves to
be able to
question you know talk about him really
either critically or
in a sort of well advocate advocatory
manner if that's a word but um yeah no
uh hmm yeah now i can't really answer
that question probably sorry but um
ignore is the best answer you know thank
you okay
okay cool um i am seeing
uh a lot of questions from the same few
people so i'd encourage you if you
haven't submitted a question yet
and there's one on your mind yeah
please do stick it in the chat um
yeah peter do you want to ask your
question
sure so do you think it could be
dangerous if neo-nihilism gains traction
and followers due to a misunderstanding
it with uh uh i should say less
sophisticated colloquial understanding
of power that it currently exists
like might makes right type thing or do
you think neo nihilism is inherently an
elitist philosophy
only for the elites
um well i think it can get out of hand
and i remember actually and one one of
the reasons i moved on from it a little
bit is because um
i don't know if this is true but someone
told me once that i think it's in mexico
there'd been a
number of little group who'd read this
and in a criminal manner using criminal
manner
some kind of gang um so there is that
danger
um and this is why the
text is only available in print actually
there is a danger for abuse
um with regard to it being an elite
thing no i don't think so i think um
it this is i mean this
is really for everyone and in a way if
people really read and
read this studied this there'd be less
conflict because you'd realize you know
there is no answer as to whether tea is
better than coffee
whether abortion is right or wrong you
know there is no fundamental fact of the
matter
and in a way this would uh maybe ease
tensions
if you consider that to be desirable
which is of course not
not an objective fact i'm reading
spinoza at the moment and he
really said the same thing you know
there's the more one
knows the facts of the matter the less
conflict there will occur often
conflicts occur because
uh one person or one group thinks
something's absolutely right a way
behaves absolutely right
another group will think this is
absolutely wrong and they'll just debate
it
but you know fundamentally neither of
them are are right
so i think it's not an elitist thing
however of course
um it is in one's interest sometimes if
one was founding us
if i for example were founding a state i
wouldn't advocate the reading of this
because it's obviously in the interest
of a statesman states person
to
make people believe that morals are
objective and it's much
more easy to control people that way of
course so the question
as to um it's whether one should
proliferate this is really dependent on
who is speaking what position they're in
and they said there's no absolute
there's no absolute answer to even that
question
i got a follow-up uh and um
[Music]
so yeah that you kind of answered what i
was going to say is that um
in order to gain power one must
off-escape
their desire for power uh at times and
given the context or the domain
um but would you say that having an
explicit um
awareness of power and and stating that
you have power kind of ameliorates
the more pathological effects that lead
to the unnecessary suffering
um i mean this was spinoza's view that
the you know
pers you know peace of mind is achieved
through
further understanding you know i mean if
you um
if you understand people's psychology
you're much less willing to judge them
you know if you know their background
and so on you know you know why they
acting this way you know why they
believe this you know it sort of makes
sense
and that stops one's own emotional
reaction to that
um and generally i think um you know the
more knowledge one acquires
the more peaceful one becomes really um
but that's not again an objective desire
that's if you want to become peaceful
you know
if you want to achieve peace of mind
other people may want to be more
adventurous
and get thrills and so on so forth you
know so again it really is
it's very very much a matter of
perspective um
so that you just cannot give general
answers to these questions because
there are no general truths uh
ultimately
with regard to it in my view
but of course i understand this is a
very contentious unusual view very
controversial view so most people won't
agree with it
um obviously people's sense of right and
wrong
is part of their self-identity so if you
start questioning that they'll become
you know like very defensive and think
well this is then i've misunderstood you
know
my whole life and my role the role in my
life and so on you know so i understand
that
it's the same philosophy of mind when
you start questioning what the mind is
this is my main field really flush your
mind you know you start questioning
people's you know sense of self or ego
or
or desire whatever it is you know they
suddenly become very very defensive and
aggressive
because you're questioning a person's
own identity as i say
um this is as well but that's what sort
of makes it more exciting you know it's
like
i mean it's not there's nothing worse
than just people just trudging along
with the same old concepts right
so and even you know at the very least
it's
it it's sort of um it's a matter for
debate
but like i say ultimately um i've i've
although i wrote this quite a few years
ago now
um i've never come across any refutation
of it you know
cool not to say there isn't one i'm
always open-minded to refutation
but i so far haven't i haven't read one
so
yeah so i think you know
but uh another side effect of this of
course is that it kind of
makes it kind of pushes you away from
society in a way that's not necessarily
personally positive
so when you see these great debates
about you know you know certain
politicians or
or movements or whatever you've got this
kind of
cold distance from it all we think well
i'm looking at 20
early beginning of the early 20th
century here this is what kind of people
starting to believe now
uh this is the same as it was 300 years
ago whatever and this will move on
you know um and that's not really i mean
that's
sometimes it's good to get down in and
um
start arguing arguing for but you can do
that with neo analysis you see because
ultimately neonism says that there are
you know there are no objective values
but there are subjective values
so i have my own preferences i don't
want a tyrannical world you know i don't
want um
certain people to be in power because
it's i don't want like a third of
england
to be owned by the old aristocracy from
a thousand you know
as developed a thousand years ago by
william the conqueror that's not in my
personal interest
so i might then you know issue decrees
that try to mitigate
these um obstacles to my own power
ultimately on my own development
and that's abs there's nothing wrong
with that you know this is actually life
this is what life does you know
even bacteria uh they seek their own
advantage you know or their group's
advantage family advantage
against others you know so this is just
the way this is descriptive
element of reality um but if uh
you know but you know most creatures
don't
have normative ethics they don't you
know sharks don't say you know you
should swim around us now and again when
we get hungry this is a good thing
they don't do that humans can do that
but it's um ultimately as i say in the
book somewhere
um morality itself is a power structure
it's a way of us trying to get what we
want you know
mostly subconsciously unwittingly so um
i don't
you know when people put themselves on
moral pedestal and say this person's
just disgrace or one
this is the ideal society you know what
they're really doing is they're trying
to
gain power themselves but they won't be
conscious of that fact you know this is
a way that nature works
through human conceptuality um but
ultimately it comes down to this
i think
cool cool sam do you want to ask your
question
uh sure and i'm actually noticing that
uh rayne's comment just hit that pretty
directly
um i was just kind of noting to myself
uh when peter and rachel were having an
exchange that there was clear
distinction being made between uh
i'd say niches that we'd be proud of and
ones that we might be more embarrassed
of
um so there's a vector of judgment
happening there clearly not of a moral
basis
and uh i was wondering is this is this
an aesthetic judgment
that's uh playing out here though reigns
reigns comment here
um just uh touched on purse's
argument that it has to do with uh the
capacity to
uh adhere to uh those who can
kind of engage with logical arguments
either
in a uh good faith or accurate way or
rather a fallacious way so i think
there's there was definitely some of
that going on
but i'm curious what your thoughts are
beyond that
uh okay so um
the judgment about nietzscheans one
might be embarrassed about i mean that
was yeah that's uh an
aesthetic judgment um i'm not telling
them how to behave
um and if i were if i said you know you
guys should shut up
that would be an expression of my
subjective valuation
i'm not i would not be claiming that
it's an objective fact that you guys
have to shut up
that would be a contradiction but of
course it's not wrong to contradict
oneself
you know it's not an immoral thing to do
under this doctrine
so i could contradict myself and
willingly deceive people
which would not be wrong because there's
no such thing as ultimate wrong
um it would just be a mode of my power
uh or attempted power expression
that answers the first little bit of
your question um
did you have a second uh question that
you can formulate in a
proposition you you address the
aesthetic component
uh quite dead on there so yeah um
yeah i mean anitra of course speaks a
lot about i don't know what
nietzsche talks about aesthetics a lot
you know and tragedy and
and the dionysian world view i mean um
but you know interestingly
i um you know bring
i became interested in whitehead after
nature alfred north whitehead
1947. and um he
he thinks as an as you know for
nietzsche there's this fundamental
level of will to power which whitehead
interestingly is interested in and he
had the notebooks will the power
got a copy of it annotated um
but for whitehead uh the fundamental
drive of the universe is more than
simply power
it's also beauty and um
this is an interesting component that
i'm currently looking into
um but i won't talk about it now i mean
that's another podcast by whitehead
but um i'm not sure if fundamentally the
ultimate
level of reality is is power only i
think powers you know it's very
ambiguous term as well and you know
it's quite reductive in a way you know
so
however um even if
you question that fundamental metaphysic
you know what
lies under physicality um whether it be
power us
an aesthetic drive or a drive to
knowledge or something else
um still the fact remains that if you
make
a moral um uh judgment
or proposition like um like i said one
or not to murder
um that has to be you have to still give
reasons to substantiate that
normally one thing i didn't mention is
this difference
between hypothetical and categorical
imperatives so hypothetical imperative
is um an is a
a means and an end expressed with an if
clause so like
you know if i if you want if you don't
want to
go to jail you ought not to murder
people right
now that is um an ought that is
perfectly legitimate it's got an if
clause if
one does not want to go to jail well no
not to murder people
okay so i don't want to go to jail and i
therefore
i don't i don't want i or not to mother
people
i also have no desire to murder people
either
but prescriptive morality um especially
issuing from kant
is usually devised in terms of
categorical imperatives where there's no
if clause so it's simply
one or not to murder and for can if you
add an if clause
it suddenly becomes very subjective but
the neo-nihilist
doctrine then is that um all
moral propositions are hypothetical they
all have a nif clause
um even if it's implicit you know so um
and that's usually you know one ought to
follow the law
if one wants to live in a harmonious
society okay
so that most people do want to live in a
harmonious society where they can
use zoom and write books and so on and
so forth and get on with their friends
most people want that but of course it's
not absolute you know some people don't
want to live in a harmonious society
they want to
have adventure and war and so on you
know we shouldn't forget there were gods
of war in the ancient past
and we can't say that's immoral because
then that again that would be based on
um you know an absolute standard
so um yeah
so um this distinction
so you can get oughts from an if but you
can't get orts from an is
and to derive an orc from an is is where
hume comes in of course this is hume's
guillotine
the azort cap you know just because
something is a certain way
doesn't mean it ought to be that way and
you see this a lot you say well
um you know we have evolved to be
compassionate to one another therefore
we ought to be compassionate to one
another
i mean this is just a nonsexy secret it
doesn't
does not follow it's um you could just
say by the same principle say we have
evolved aggression therefore we ought to
be aggressive
uh but nonetheless despite this simple
point um
it's often often uh committed to this
fallacy
next question
okay uh jvt do you want to ask yours
gbt
yes i i'd be glad to so peter
um since you mentioned bergson and
whitehead
and and of course nietzsche i'm
wondering
you've already explained somewhat how
whitehead
and his notion of beauty and perhaps
related to that creativity
uh might be related to nature but i'm
wondering about
bergson's elan vital also
as a kind of notion
of self-organizing emergence
within subjectivity in time and how that
connects to the will to power i'm just
wondering you know since you've
moved on from nietzsche i'm just
wondering how some of the
um individuals you've studied then
caused you to reflect back on your neo
nihilism um i mean that's a profound
question which i couldn't do justice to
but i'll
i'll give it a start um so the land
vital
sort of vital impulse in burgsson is a
creative impulse
that lies within all life for bergson um
there are similarities between bergson
and nietzsche
i mean you know like um in the last
sentence i think of his last bergson's
last book where is it now
um he says he talks about the over man
you know the superman you know there's
this
there's this belief i mean nietzsche has
got this notion of the uberman she
doesn't really fit in that nicely to his
philosophy but
it's he's very ambiguous about it um
it's
translated as superman over man whatever
um and
bergson's ilan bergson's created he's
got a book called creative evolution
then as you probably know
and um he believes in a teleology in
nature so that evolution is working
in a way that's not completely random
but there is actually a standard
to which things are evolving and as they
meet
certain species meets a certain obstacle
they will evolve around that and that's
where you get the multiplicity of
species
but then nonetheless for bugs on the air
there's this ultimate
um goal towards which the elan vertile
is going
um and ultimately he says
you know famous in this lovely uh
sentence the purpose of the universe is
to create gods or something like this
right
um and so there you know there's
interesting analogies with nietzsche
there
he also talks about bergson also talks
about the imminence and whitehead as
well you know this is
actually i must say i mean it was
nietzsche who really got me into
through you know with it was nietzsche
got me into this
um into bergson and whitehead because
you know the will to power really
is um an imminence
like a subjectivity not consciousness
but of sort of drive then of a pulse you
know like a pathos he says
within all things he says at least in
his notebooks
um and this is very similar to the
elaine vitale in a way
uh of course for books and they learn
about is not just about power but
actually in many ways
you can you can read it that way you
know the purpose of perception is to see
more things around you
um that are that one can practically act
upon
thus empowering a person in other words
or a species so like making them develop
more and more
so there's a lot of interesting um
parallels
i'll also say that when i was at warwick
university um
my lecturer was keith ansel pearson
who's like especially some both bugs on
anita so
so uh he's i'm sure he's written a lot
of interesting stuff about this much
more interesting than what i'm saying
but yeah no there's certainly the
parallels and of course in
whitehead there's you know he's known as
a pan experientialist now we're getting
to plan psychism
um whereby there is this element of
subjectivity again not consciousness
but there is a striving in spinoza
there's cannatis a striving
in leibniz there's a dominant monad
which is a striving to develop you know
it wasn't and then of course in shopping
is will to live so it's not like a new
thing in nature
um i can i uh just just
uh just do a quick follow-up and those
other folks that need to get in
but um i'm just wondering if
so basically you said that in in
propositional terms
uh you cannot validate
morality but if we take john verveigh's
notion of
four different types of knowledge uh
from
the propositional to the procedural
perspectival and participatory
and not just the propositional which you
is what you're basing yours on
if you look at the participatory and as
we
engage inter-subjectively with other
people
that we can say that there are things
that we can
do and not do say and not say that is
beneficial
both or not beneficial to oneself
as well as to the other person and
and i think you you can you can draw
some lines
that would you know be clear you can
look at it both
you can look at that you know harm to
them physically mentally
emotionally i mean so there's ways of of
i think framing morality
uh other than just propositionally okay
i mean i should know this i haven't read
um for veggie but i'm speaking with him
on the weekend so i should learn this
quickly
um um yeah no interesting i mean okay
so the interesting thing about uh
whitehead compared to nietzsche here is
that
why it talks about good and evil but
also in a kind of relative sense in
which he says you know there are
the epochs um which strive towards a
certain harmony
and evil is the fragmentation of that
harmony
and um so you get a lot of you get
protest theology
theologians who try to uh bring back
christianity into this whitehead now was
a christian then he became uh an atheist
and then he became
theist again but never a christian again
but i should say this yeah that
for whitehead evil and fragmentation of
social of
social purpose and you can understand
that because whitehead's view of
reality was much more integrated so you
know he talks about perceptions
prehension
so when you see something that becomes
part of you it's not just you
as an individual a post and this is it
needs to be more individualistic in this
sense you know
it's you know me against the world in a
way although he says the self is a
hierarchy of wills
um and so it absolutely is the case that
it's in one's interest to harmonize um
with others around one harmonize with
the world
ultimately um however two things i'd say
against that
number one a lot of people would say
that's a hypothetical
you don't have to put it into
propositional formats but
in a way it's it's selfish it's not
altruism ultimately it's egoism isn't it
because
you know is in my benefit that i get on
with everyone right
now some people would um you know
certain moralists would say well that's
that's not a problem around you that's
selfishness you know disguise the mouth
another thing is second aspect is
um what is beneficial
to one's group one's family nation or
whatever it may be
it's sometimes um antagonistic towards
another group
um so like um
i don't know like uh you know sharing
water amongst certain number
in in one's group um of course that
would be antagonistic to another group
we wanted that water
and now of course ultimately if you
shared it all let's say then there would
be
there wouldn't be enough water for all
so you'd have to make this
um distinction that um morality then is
is um conducive to a group a social
harmony
um but it can't be conducive to all you
know because ultimately
uh there's composition for resources and
there's also
differences and desires like i said
before you know sometimes
we assume that peace and harmony is what
everyone wants but i wouldn't you know
look at history
and around the world you do that's not
necessarily the case
and even if it were the case how could
you prove that to be an objective fact
that one all ought to aim for peace and
harmony now i say this
you know purely uh uh rationally of
course i myself
i think i'm very sort of harmonious with
my friends and family and
the little village living here in
cornwall and so on you know
um but i still maintain
that ultimately you can't um
you can't sanction this you know
ultimately you know
um and that you know can actually be
beneficial
to stopping conflict as i say sometimes
but at the same time why would you want
to stop conflict you know this is again
another moral
you know um conflict you know we would
not have evolved
as again nietzsche but we would not have
evolved into the
complex organisms that we are were it
not for many
obstacles obstacles and conflicts down
the road
you know he doesn't think suffering is
bad necessarily a bad thing
you know or obstacles are a bad thing
this is again a form of a christian
a legacy of christianity well we need we
need
i'm gonna i just want to say that one
thank you when i was on
i mentioned the concept of antagonistic
cooperation as peter well knows
i just want to leave that there i'll
look into that
good question thank you
squeeze in one more question i think
before the hour um
dan do you want to ask your question
about sociopathy
uh sure let me see if i can find it here
um
it's been a very active okay
if uh if power
is the driving ethos in neo nihilism
is this philosophy inherently unethical
amoral perhaps even sociopathic
lacking a system of meta values
such as interpersonal dignity collective
well-being
and personal integrity personal
integrity kind of
integrity with self and also intel
integrity with
with the ecosystem um
i'd say yes it is an amoralism yes
um with regards to the other things i
don't know what you mean by meta values
can you elaborate on that um it was
something that came up in a discussion
again i'm not sure if i'm saying his
name correctly greg and enriquez
who's a uh a psychotherapist
uh that was in a a dialogue or a
dialogue
with um john verveiki
as well as jordan hall and this was a
this was something he introduced the
psychotherapist
introduced as a system i guess a system
of
i guess if you're going to have what
what john vervinky calls this reciprocal
opening or this unconditional love or
this
then then having a fundamental
system of meta values helps
for the cohesion social cohesion and
and communitas and and cooperation and
collaboration and things of this nature
okay uh well i just i mean i would call
those mental values just values
uh you know it's just not a good class
of it um
you know does it if you ask the question
does this lead to the
sort of um halting of cooperation and so
on
um it can do
but but needn't but if it does
who's to say that is wrong i mean this
is
like meta there's sort of the assumption
that you know there are we you know
again it's an assumption of morality
saying that cooperation is a good thing
integration is a good thing uh
being you know um golden rule is a good
thing i mean this is uh
this is exactly what i'm questioning i'm
saying how do you substantiate those
claims
you know it's complete control or delete
i mean i i mean i i hear you on one
perspective but you can have a situation
for exa
i forget what like if you take the gini
coefficient if you i forget if it's a
one or a zero
let's say you have a million people
in a community and that one person in
the community has
absolutely all of the power and everyone
else has
no power no wealth um
you could look at it from the stand i
mean one measure
you could say is that society going to
exist
or is it going to let you know you there
are some
measure is it resilient is it going to
survive
in you know in the in the biosphere
okay i mean this is a descriptive
question though isn't it still it's like
well this probably won't survive
and that's just the way it is um but if
you were to say
therefore that tyrant or whatever ought
to distribute his wealth
resources or whatever um you know you
know
according to what if what um if he wants
to survive okay well in that case yeah
he will and that's
you know why most uh tyrants never last
you know as spinoz even said
but um and plato even ultimately but um
how about if you know um someone just
wants to
achieve ultimate power for a very
fragmentary
time i mean although it's an unusual
thing uh to desire
it's not a desire can't be wrong i mean
this is
hume's famous um expression that is not
contrary
to prefer the destruction of the whole
world to the scratching of my finger
this is uh just a matter of you know
it's not again there's no contrary to
reason
of course it is very unusual but you
can't say to that tyrant well you know
you should distribute your wealth you
you could say you should distribute your
wealth if you want to survive
and then if he does want to survive
which you presume you would then he
might
um and also from those
beings that are under him of course they
would want to
denigrate destroy his power and you can
under understand that you know
on the space of will to power and you
can just understand how these things
play out
but ultimately there's no um objective
transcendent standard by which you say
you know all power should be distributed
equally this is
this is not a fact of the world
i'm noticing we're out of time but this
was this was a super cool discussion
thank you so much peter for
coming and having this this conversation
with us and thank you guys all for your
really awesome questions
uh so it's gonna happen now i'm gonna
hand it back to peter lindberg he's
gonna
announce some upcoming events and close
off the space and after that we're gonna
hang out for a bit and do some like
dangerous space type games and
discussions where we process some of
this
some of this event so you can feel free
to go after the announcements or you can
stay for another
half hour or so and we're gonna we're
gonna do some post event conversations
so i'll hand it off to you peter
thank you um so i'll make some
announcements in the morning at the
moment but
uh peter my friend thank you so much for
coming to the
stoat today and and uh having your ideas
uh stress tested by all the meta weirdos
here that uh congregate at the the stoa
that's really fun really fun great
anything
anything you'd like to leave us off with
or like maybe what's the places we can
find you or your work or
what you're doing next well i yeah
i'm based exit to university um well in
theory
when the global situation calms down but
otherwise yeah online philosopher.eu
um i'm gonna twitter handle peter
schuster h
instagram facebook facebook onto
logistics where i just
you know i'm not constantly reading
stuff so i just you know sort of quote
interesting lines i read every
most days um yeah so but yeah twitter's
probably the best place
cool all right um so upcoming events uh
we got one later today 6 p.m eastern
time
the folks from future thinkers uv and
mike are going to talk about the smart
village
they are creating um so that should be
fun and
on thursday we got a special guest
angus callard she's going to come in to
do a talk a lecture
can you know you are wrong and angus
is um what is she again she's like a
professor associate professor at the
university of chicago and author of a
book
aspiration the agency of becoming so
that should be super cool
we've got tons of events like we have on
next monday we got what we got derek
jensen we got alexander dugan we got
like john zurz in the next day it's all
these like
you know if this place doesn't get
canceled then you know we're doing
something right here
and ariel friedman will be doing post
dangerous spaces discussions after those
ones as well
uh so if you like what we're doing you
can feel free to support us on patreon
and then more events on the website
so that being said uh we'll go on a
quick bio break and then i'll take an
ariel and we'll do the danger
space not recorded again thank you
everyone